Gordimer mss., LMC 2355
Lilly Library
Gordimer mss.
1934-1991
Lilly Library
Gordimer, Nadine.
LMC 2355
29 Boxes
Consists of the papers of South African author and Nobel prize winner Nadine Gordimer. The correspondence is mostly with her colleagues, literary agents and publishers, including magazines such as The New Yorker where many of her short stories first appeared. There are draft and final versions of Gordimer's stories, articles, book reviews, novels, short story collections, speeches, etc. The notebooks contain story ideas, working notes, as well as dates of completion and publication for some of the stories. Completing the collection is a diary kept by Gordimer when she was eleven years old.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Gordimer was born in Springs, South Africa in 1923. At age 13 she began her writing career, her first writings appearing in the children's section of the Johannesburg Sunday Express. Since then she has written novels and countless short stories, articles, etc. which have been published in magazines and newspapers worldwide. Many of her works reflect the political and social dilemmas of living under apartheid in South Africa and consequently, several of her books have been banned in that country until very recently.
Among her numerous awards are the Booker Prize for Fiction (1974), Modern Language Association of America award (1982), and the Premio Malaparte prize (1987). In 1991 Gordimer's entire body of work was honored with the Nobel Prize in Literature. She has been decorated Commandeur de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres (France) and has received honorary degrees from such institutions as Harvard and Yale Universities.
Apart from her many achievements in writing, Gordimer has been visiting professor and lecturer at several American universities. She is a founder and executive member of the Congress of South African Writers and has encouraged and supported new writers, especially young African authors and poets.
Arrangement/Organization
Organized in the following series: I. Correspondence, II. Writings, III. Diaries and Notebooks, IV. Miscellaneous, V. Additions.
Scope and Content Note
Consists of the papers of South African author and Nobel prize winner Nadine Gordimer. The correspondence is mostly with her colleagues, literary agents and publishers, including magazines such as The New Yorker where many of her short stories first appeared. There are draft and final versions of Gordimer's stories, articles, book reviews, novels, short story collections, speeches, etc. The notebooks contain story ideas, working notes, as well as dates of completion and publication for some of the stories. Completing the collection is a diary kept by Gordimer when she was eleven years old.
Correspondents include: Cyrilly Abels, Chinua Achebe, Roger Angell, Frank Rosslyn Bradlow, Thelma Gutsche, Trevor Huddleston, Roland Joffe, George William Lanning, Bernth Lindfors, Frank McShane, Herbert Mitgang, Alan Stewart Paton, Es'kia Mphahlele, Michael Scammell, Harvey Shapiro, Rowland James Smith, James Stern, Efua Theodora Morgue Sutherland, Paul Theroux, Per Erik Wastberg, Katherine Sergeant Angell White, and Helen Yglesias.
Manuscripts Index in the library includes entries at item level.
Acquisition Information
Purchase. 1993.
Gordimer, Nadine.; Achebe, Chinua.; Angell, Roger.; Bradlow, Frank Rosslyn, 1913-; Gutsche, Thelma.; MacShane, Frank.; Paton, Alan.; Sutherland, Efua Theodora.; Theroux, Paul.; White, Katharine Sergeant Angell.; Yglesias, Helen.
- Correspondence, 1948-1989; (Box 1 - Box 4, folder 24)
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence is divided into a chronological file dated 1948-1989 and an alphabetical file consisting chiefly of Gordimer's correspondence with literary agents and publishers. Among the correspondents are: Cyrilly Abels, Chinua Achebe, Roger Angell, Frank Rosslyn Bradlow, Thelma Gutsche, Trevor Huddleston, Roland Joffé, George William Lanning, Bernth Lindfors, Frank MacShane, Herbert Mitgang, Es'kia Mphahlele, Alan Stewart Paton, Michael Scammell, Harvey Shapiro, Rowland James Smith, James Stern, Efua Theodora Morgue Sutherland, Paul Theroux, Per Erik Wästberg, Katharine Sergeant Angell White, Helen Yglesias. Consult the Manuscripts Index for dates of letters of individual correspondents.
  - 1948 - 1973 (Box 1)
  - 1974 - 1989 (Box 2)
  - A.P. Watt & Son (literary agent - UK), 1965-1978; (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd., 1960-1975; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - The New Yorker, 1950-1978; 1987-1988; (12 folders) (Box 3)
  - Russell & Volkening, Inc. (literary agent - US), 1956-1980; (9 folders) (Box 3)
  - Satenstein, Sidney (literary agent - US), 1950-1961; (9 folders) (Box 3)
  - Shirley Collier Agency (literary agent - US), 1961-1978; (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Simon & Schuster, Inc., 1951-1959; (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Victor Gollancz, Ltd., 1953-1976; (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - Viking Press, Inc., 1958-1985; (14 folders) (Box 4)
    General
    royalty statements
- Writings, (Box 4, folder 21 - Box 15, folder 80)
  Includes early writings, articles, book reviews, novels, scripts, short stories, short story collections, speeches, etc. All annotations, amendments, and corrections in Gordimer's hand, unless otherwise noted. Descriptions of individual writings were taken from Gordimer's inventory. Arranged in alphabetical order by title after the Early Writings which are arranged by date. Consult Index to Titles for complete listing of locations for each title.
  - Early Writings; Abroad - Black Interpreters (Box 4)
    - Early Writings: (Box 4, Folder 21)
      The Quest for Sun Gold - first published story, photocopy from The Sunday Express, Johannesburg, June 13, 1937
      The Valley Legend - tear sheet from Children's Sunday Express, Sept. 18, 1938
      editor's mention (Auntie Ban Writes) of other stories published by Gordimer in same newspaper
      Spring (poem) - clipping
      two school exercise books with reviews of "Books read in 1938"
    - The First Circle [play], 1944[?]. (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Won Drama Award and was performed by Johannesburg Repertory Society. Carbon copy
    - Unfinished and untitled novel, written before 1946. (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Typed fragment
    - University writings. University of the Witwatersrand., 1946 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      Ten essays and class exercises, with teacher's comments and marks awarded.
    - Short stories, written before 1950: (Box 4, Folder 25)
      At three o'clock in the morning someone wakes me[first line]; Babe; The Hero; It Might Happen This Way...; The Old World and the New World; On Sunday mornings in Johannesburgh I take a bus somewhere [first line]; The Shoes; The Sleep and the Waking; They were back home again, all three of them [first line]
    - Old Times' Sake [short story],., 1949/50 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      Final[?] version
    - Abroad [short story],., July 1966 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      Published in The Southern Review. Original version
    - Across the Veld [short story],., 1989 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Adapted from section of My Son's Story and published in Paris Review, 1989. Photocopy of final version; final version as published
    - Africa Emergent [short story],., July 1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Included in Livingstone's Companions. Original and final versions
    - The African Magician [short story]. (Box 4, Folder 30)
      Final version[?]
    - The African Pot [essay]. (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Zeit Magazin (Germany) feature in which writers, artists, etc., were commissioned to write about favorite works of art. Original and final versions
    - After Apartheid: Black and White in a New South Africa [address]., Aug. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      The Anatomy of Hate: Solving Conflict Through Dialogue and Democracy conference held by the Norwegian Nobel Prize Committee and the Elie Wiesel Foundation of New York in Oslo, Norway, Aug. 1990.
      Original first draft and reading copy.
    - Alberto Moravia's Africa. Review of Which Tribe Do You Belong To? by Alberto Moravia., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      Published in London Magazine, 1974. Final version
    - Allan Boesak: Choosing for Justice [documentary],., 1983 (Box 4, Folder 34-36)
      Script outline; titles; paper edit of final script; notes; transcripts of interviews; transcript of Boesak's interviews in film; printed text of Gordimer's statement introducing film at first public showing in New York; announcements of film showing; review clippings
    - Amnesty [short story]. (Box 4, Folder 37)
      Published in The New Yorker and included in Jump and Other Stories. Tear sheet from The New Yorker
    - Apartheid [article]., Apr. 1959 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      Published in Holiday, Apr. 1959. Tear sheet from Holiday
    - Apartheid, the Agitator [article]., June 27, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      Clipping, dated June 27, 1976
    - Art and Change [speech]. (Box 4, Folder 40)
      To open the Aquarius National Student Arts Festival. Draft version
    - As I See South Africa Today [address]., June 27, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Delivered in Durban to the Catholic Winter School, June 27, 1976. Reading copy[?]
    - At Last--Luangwa! [travel essay],., July/Aug. 1987; 1987 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      Commissioned by Washington Post Magazine, 1987
      also published in Sunday Times, London, 1987.
      Notebook; original draft version; loose notes for photographs; final version; final shortened version, published by Sunday Times
    - At the Crossroads of Cultures. Review of Morning Yet On Creation Day, by Chinua Achebe., Oct. 17, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      Originally titled: Achebe, Gift of Africa. Published by Times Literary Supplement, Oct. 17, 1975. Final version; tear sheet from TLS
    - Balancing Rocks[short story],., 1985 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      Excerpt from A Sport of Nature. Final version
    - A Beautiful Day, Com [article]. (Box 4, Folder 45)
      Published in The Observer, London. Final version as sent to editor Donald Trelford
    - Benoni--Son of Sorrow[short story],., Apr. 1988 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Adapted from novel My Son's Story and published in Prize Writing, edited by Martin Goff. Final version as published; photocopy of final version
    - The Black Interpreters: Notes on African Writing. Published Spro-Cas/Ravan,., 1973; Feb. 1972 (Box 4, Folder 47-49)
      Section One "Modern African Fiction in English" published under title: African Literature: The Lectures Given on this Theme at the University of Cape Town's Public Summer School by Board of Extra-Mural Studies, University of Cape Town, Feb. 1972. Section One: Origins and Directions - eight versions and revised pages. Several marked "First lecture"
      - Section One: Themes - three versions, two marked "Second lecture" (Box 4, Folder 50-51)
        revised pages; themes of various works by other authors
  - The Black Interpreters (cont'd) - Burger's Daughter (Box 5)
    - The Black Interpreters (cont'd) (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Section One: Politics as Fate - five versions, one marked "Third lecture"; revised pages
      - Section Two: New Black Poetry in South Africa - two versions (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
        tear sheets from The Dalhousie Review; poems by various authors
      - Contents, chapter headings, bibliography (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Two copies of African Literature: The Lectures..., one incomplete (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Writings by others, arranged alphabetically by author (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Clippings for research (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Bride of Christ [short story],., July 1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Original version
    - A Brilliant Bigot. Review of Sarah Gertrude Millin: A South African Life by Martin Rubin., Sept. 15, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Published in The Times Literary Supplement, Sept. 15, 1978. Clipping from TLS
    - Burger's Daughter [novel]. Viking,., 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10-14)
      Original version; photostat of original version
      - Discarded versions of various sections; notes, queries and corrections; analysis of structure and contents of novel after most of it was written and epigraphs as used in final version (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
      - Incomplete clean copy, without final revisions made in, July 1978 (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
        penultimate copy of final version
      - Photocopy, with final corrections and revised pages inserted; model pages for typist (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
  - Burger's Daughter (cont'd) - The Credibility Gap (Box 6)
    - Burger's Daughter (cont'd) Research materials; three notebooks (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
      - Reviews of book (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Address to the CNA (Central News Agency) Award dinner., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Final version as delivered; two clippings about award dinner
    - Bush-craft [short story],., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Excerpted and adapted from July's People. Original and final versions
    - By the Light of 10,000 Bulbs. Review of The Visitation, by Ahmed Essop., Feb. 11, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Published in The Star, Johannesburg,Feb. 11, 1981. Original and final versions; clipping from The Star
    - Censors, Poets, and Apartheid [article],., 1972 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Published in The New York Times. Final version
    - Censorship and its Aftermath [address]., June 2, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Keynote address to International Writers' Day, P.E.N. International, June 2, 1990. Final version
    - Censorship--The Final Solution [article]., 1989 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Published in Evening Standard, London, 1989. Final version
    - Chief Luthuli [article]., 1959; May 1958 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
      Included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places, shortened versions published in Atlantic Monthly, 1959 and Treason Trial Bulletin, May 1958. Original version; final version; shortened version; various drafts; copy of Treason Trial Bulletin, No. 2, with article
    - Children with the House to Themselves [short story],., 1985; 1986 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      Excerpt from A Sport of Nature and published in Paris Review, 1986. Final version
    - A Chip of Glass Ruby [script],., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      Draft script, with changes; final script with changes
    - A Christmas in the South [short story]. (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Adapted from first novel The Lying Days. Final version[?]
    - City Lovers. Lincoln Center program for New York Film Festival, Sept. 1982 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - The Colour of Want. Review of The Race War by Ronald Segal., 1967 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Published in The Nation, 1967. Final version
    - A Company of Laughing Faces [short story]. (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Published in Mademoiselle and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Original version[?]
    - Congo [essay],., 1960 (Box 6, Folder 24-26)
      Two part travel essay commissioned by Holiday. Adapted and published in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places under the title: The Congo River. Original version and two second drafts of "Africa 1960: The Great Period"; original version and two second drafts of "Towards the Heart of Darkness: Congo River Journey"; research material
    - The Conservationist [novel]. J. Cape, and Viking,., 1974; 1975; 28 June 1973 (Box 6, Folder 27-30)
      Original first version dated 28 June 1973; original version of parts of the novel; final version for typist and additions
      - Bound page proofs of Penguin edition (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - Research materials; notebook, dated 1970-73, also contains notes for short story:The Credibility Gap (Box 6, Folder 32-33)
    - Photocopy of address to the CNA Award dinner, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - The Conservationist [short story]., Mar. 1973 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      Adapted from the novel The Conservationist. Published in Playboy, Mar. 1973 (v.20, no.3). Two versions of first chapter of novel; tear sheet from Playboy
    - A Correspondence Course [short story],., Dec. 1979 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      Published in The New Yorker and included in Something Out There. Original version; photocopy of original version; corrected version; final version[?]; typescript with editor's comments
    - A Correspondence Course [script],., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Notes; photocopy of draft
    - Country Lovers [script],., 1978 (Box 6, Folder 38-41)
      Adapted from "Town and Country Lovers." Original version, Nov. 1978; revised version; original final version, Aug. 13, 1981; photocopy with revisions; revised and abandoned pages
    - Contracts (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Publications Appeal Board materials (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - The Credibility Gap [short story],., Aug.-Nov. 1970 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - David Goldblatt--So Far - Great Problems in the Street (Box 7)
    - David Goldblatt--So Far., 1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Introduction to catalogue of his retrospective exhibition of photographs at the National Gallery, Cape Town, 1983; shortened version given as opening address at exhibition. Notes; original version; two final versions; shortened version
    - A Day in My Life [article]., 1989; 1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Feature for Asani Shiubun, Japan, 1989 and published in English in The Independent, London, 1990. Final version
    - Death, Love and the Fruit-Basket on Carmen Miranda's Head. Review of Sergeant Getúlio by João Ubaldo Ribeiro and Sol by Mario Salz., 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Published in London Magazine, 1980. Final version
    - The Delmas Trial [address]. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      19th African American Institute Conference, Lusaka, Zambia, Jan. 9-13, 1989. Final version
    - Diagonal Street [documentary]. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Directed by Lynton Stephenson. First version, two copies of second version, and third version
      - Transcription and editing of taped interviews (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Notes; clippings for research (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - Divers with Bloodshot Eyes [article],., late 50s/early 60s (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Commissioned by Holiday. Final version
    - The Dogs [short story]. (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Excerpted from The Conservationist. Galley proofs
    - Don Mattera [essay]. (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Final version
    - English-Language Literature and Politics in South Africa [lecture]., April 4-7, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
      Barnard College, New York (Gildersleeve Lecture), n.d.; Conference on Literature in the Conditions of Southern Africa, April 4-7, 1975, York University, England; University of Cape Town Summer School, Feb. 1972 and Jan. 1976. Eight versions with notes; bibliography
    - The Essential Gesture: Writers and Responsibility [lecture]., 1984 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      University of Michigan (Tanner Lecture), 1984 and published in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places (London: Jonathan Cape, 1988). Original manuscript; second draft; five pages of notes; final version as presented, marked for reading
    - The Fischer Case [article],., 1966 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      Published in New York Times Magazine and London Magazine and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. Final version for NYTM; photocopy of tear sheet from London Magazine, Mar. 1966
    - The Flickering Image: Cinema and the Rights of Man in South Africa [speech]., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      Journée Droits de L'homme et Cinema, Cannes Film Festival, 1989. Final version
    - For Andrina Destiny Was Bitter., June 16, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Review of The Beadle by Pauline Smith. Published in The New York Times Book Review, June 16, 1963. Photocopy proof from NYTBR
    - For Dear Life [short story],., June-July 1975 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      Published in New Statesman, London, Jan. 14, 1977 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version
    - Friday's Footprint, and Other Stories [short story collection]. Viking., 1960 (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
      The Bridegroom; Check Yes or No; Friday's Footprint(two copies); The Gentle Art(five copies); Harry's Presence (two copies); An Image of Success; The Last Kiss (two copies); Little Willie (with alternate ending); Our Bovary; The Path of the Moon's Dark Fortnight; A Style of Her Own; A Thing of the Past
      - Final drafts, Apr. 1959 (Box 7, Folder 21)
        with handwritten corrections of the following stories: The Bridegroom; Check Yes or No; Friday's Footprint; The Gentle Art; An Image of Success; The Last Kiss; The Night the Favourite Came Home; Our Bovary; A Style of Her Own; A Thing of the Past
      - Acceptance speech for the W.H. Smith and Son Literary Award, 1960? (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - From Apartheid to Afrocentrism [paper],., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 23)
      Given at conference of the Association of University English Teachers of Southern Africa and published in English in Africa 7 (no. 1, March 1980), South African Outlook (v. 107 (1977), 181- 83) and in "The AUESTA Papers."
      Photocopy of original, with cuts and changes marked for a shortened version; photocopy as published in "The AUESTA Papers"; photocopy of several pages, possibly a discarded version of above
    - Germany to Me [article],., 1969 (Box 7, Folder 24)
      Commissioned by François Bondy for an anthology of that title. Original version; version marked "Corrected text & rewrite..."
    - Gold and the Gun [television documentary], released., June 1990 (Box 7, Folder 25-26)
      Produced by Jenny Barraclough of Barraclough/Carey productions for BBC 1 TV. World-wide distribution in the series "Frontiers." Texts; "Frontiers" scripts
      - Three notebooks kept while travelling in North-Eastern Transvaal and Kruger Park (South Africa), and Mozambique, with film crew (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - Research materials; notes; production schedule; photographs; BBC publicity postcard announcing film's debut (Box 7, Folder 28-34)
    - Golden Reclining Nudes of the Desert,., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 35)
      Excerpted from The Conservationist. Published London Magazine. Page proofs
    - Good Climate, Friendly Inhabitants [screenplay]., Jan. 2, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 36)
      Adapted by Barney Simon from Gordimer short story. Final[?] version
    - Gore-Browne of Zambia: Bwana with a Difference. Review of Black Heart: Gore-Browne and the Politics of Multi-Racial Zambia by Robert Rotberg., 1977 (Box 7, Folder 37)
      Published in The Observer, London, 1977. Final version
    - Great Problems in the Street [article],., 1963 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      For anthology I Will Still Be Moved, published by Arthur Barker, edited by Marion Friedmann, 1963, and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. Final version, lacking last page(s)
  - Guarding the Gates of Paradise - July's People (Box 8)
    - Guarding the Gates of Paradise. Commissioned and published by New York Times Magazine,., 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Original version; second draft; penultimate version; final version
    - A Guest of Honour [novel]. Viking,., 1970 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
      Draft version
      - Penultimate[?] version, with changes for final version (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Revised pages; notebook; notes, some annotated in red ink by Claude Wauthier (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - Home [short story]. (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Published in The New Yorker and included in Jump and Other Stories. Copy-edited typescript from The New Yorker; galley proofs with editor's corrections
    - How Not to Know the African [article],., Aug. 1966 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Published in Rand Daily Mail, Johannesburg, under the title "The Voices We May Not Hear" and broadcast on "Voice of America." Final version
    - Huddleston: A Sign. Contribution to festschrift for Bishop Trevor Huddleston's 75th birthday,., 1987 (Box 8, Folder 10)